[SPEAKER_01]: So, we were talking about danger in sensuality and I was wondering if we could take that further to talk about the danger in the world in general or like the aggregates, the senses, the six domains, the senses.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, we can try.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what are the aggregates then?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I've just...
[SPEAKER_01]: Right here, right now... As I'm sitting there, I'm just... sort of, you know...
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: I feel... Beautiful.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the feeling is a starting point.
[SPEAKER_02]: As we said millions of times, it's a conversion point.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, does that mean now you go and find the other aggregates?
[SPEAKER_02]: After you establish your mind upon feeling?
[SPEAKER_02]: How do you find?
[SPEAKER_02]: How do you discern the other aggregates then?
[SPEAKER_02]: How do you know there are five?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, you know, it's not an explanation.
[SPEAKER_02]: The Buddha never gave explanations.
[SPEAKER_02]: Everything he taught was open-eyed.
[SPEAKER_02]: He didn't want us to understand it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, how can then understanding the five,
[SPEAKER_02]: So, where would you look for the other aggregates, then?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm seeing things, I'm hearing things.
[SPEAKER_02]: But where does that square up from the point of your feeling?
[SPEAKER_02]: Where is it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Things you feel and things you see, how do they... That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't quite know where you're going, but like...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't want to break them down.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was... my tendency would be to just look, okay, just as this experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, when you say five aggregates, you just refer to the experience as a whole?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's kind of what I would... so, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, that's absolutely fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what it stands for, for you, at the time.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, eh... where I was going was, eh... five, three, one, whichever you want to look, it's within the one you're mindful of, the feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you wouldn't be looking for the other aggregates after the feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: The experience of the feeling enduring is the experience of the five aggregates enduring, and you emphasize the feeling, because that's the converging point.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: In other words, they're inseparable.
[SPEAKER_02]: When there's one, there's five.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's five, you can focus on one.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the problem is, people start with that, focusing on one, and then, sort of, just add up the rest, as if it's all, like, laid out there for you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you just have these five things to think about in this linear manner.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm feeling a pleasant feeling that's enduring here, in my experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_02]: My whole experience is basically founded upon the current enduring
[SPEAKER_02]: Pleasant, agreeable, feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's already the experience of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if I don't think about perception, if I don't think about intentions, it's already within it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, you'll find them within that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Always.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you were to look.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if you find them, then, if you find perception within the container of the present enduring feeling, then you can go further, if your mind develops.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you can discern other four within that perception.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Including more perception.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's five within one, within five, within one, five within five.
[SPEAKER_02]: Everywhere you look, five aggregates.
Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what we said.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whether you, you know, even if you remember previous lives, it's going to be the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because when you tend... if... the tendency to go, okay, this is feeling and that's perception...
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're basically... Oh, he's just playing in the sand.
[SPEAKER_02]: He lets himself out.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not on the basis of the experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's certainly not... you're not mindful of the feeling as that converging point.
[SPEAKER_02]: And when I say converging point, I mean
[SPEAKER_02]: No, they converge here and stay within the container of present enduring feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's how you learn how to think concretely as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not linearly or theoretically or abstractly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, now that we clarified that...
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you were talking about the danger in sexuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mmm.
[SPEAKER_01]: And... That...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think that can also be applied to, okay, so, basically, seeing here, neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that feeling could be change, could change.
[SPEAKER_01]: It has the nature to change.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, while it endures, you can discern that it's subject to change.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's... yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And where that change comes from?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's completely... See, even thinking that it comes from somewhere...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, it's the wrong question.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a form... a form of conceiving it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: You realize, this is inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_02]: As in, every change is abrupt.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I'll be subjected to it, and it's inconceivable for me to, kind of, insert myself in between the abrupt change and what's before.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's completely...
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the danger.
[SPEAKER_02]: That seems to me... That is the danger.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the reason why people would have trouble grasping the danger of it, is because you still think, to a degree, well, you fail to understand that things don't change when they disappear, or when you perceive.
[SPEAKER_02]: That means they have already changed.
[SPEAKER_02]: What you want to see is that they are subject to change while they remain the same.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, basically, yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: But most people, when they think about anicca, think about change, it's like, oh, look, look, everything is constantly changing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Look, look, look.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Everything has constantly changed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is what you can see.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you won't see... You want to see subject to change.
[SPEAKER_02]: They have... their nature is change.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, things is not changing then.
[SPEAKER_02]: This feeling is still enduring.
[SPEAKER_02]: And because of that, it's subjected to change.
[SPEAKER_01]: And whenever that happens,
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: Recognizing the feeling that's enduring, but also the whole range of possibility that is involved in that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And because the presently enduring, neither painful nor pleasant feeling, could just change at any minute into, well, pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's basically part of
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the nature of this precognitive...
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if it changes to pleasure, it's still a painful nature, because of the change, not because of what it changes to.
[SPEAKER_02]: The fact that you cannot uproot it in a sense of ownership, you cannot take possession of it, where it originates, so to speak, you're always secondary to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your experience as a whole, and that's been throughout all the lifetimes you've been around, eons and eons and eons, is always responding to what you're subjected to, on the level of the feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basic... and so, the responding to what's there, on the level of the feeling, responding to it, is basically sort of going into it, and saying... accepting it, but not just accepting the feeling, but also... but accepting this whole
[SPEAKER_01]: Sort of nature of change.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're basically going in and saying, I want this to change.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's because it has changed.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why I want it to change.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, because of the change that I cannot bear... Change is the problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because of the change that I cannot bear, I accept change.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That I cannot bear, which is why I want more change, that I cannot bear.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's a vicious circle.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why it's unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why you always keep insisting the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: If the dhamma is done as a form of management, and that's determined by your attitude, whether you use it to manage what you feel,
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, you know, everybody will start inaccurately.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if that's all you do, and never start looking for beyond that, you're never going to start practicing the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because dhamma basically frees you from being subjected to that nature.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Dhamma doesn't give you a perfect way of managing your suffering or managing your feelings.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you can only do that by escaping, by finding the escape from
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: From that which is uncontrollable.
[SPEAKER_02]: Uncontrollable, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Unownable, that is subject to change.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what is the escape from that?
[SPEAKER_02]: Seeing the danger.
[SPEAKER_02]: Seeing the danger in what?
[SPEAKER_02]: In everything that
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you're not seeing the danger in the outcome?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not seeing the danger... Well, not even, like, seeing the danger in what, like, oh, there's a pleasant feeling enduring?
[SPEAKER_02]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, it's the nature of what's there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Seeing the danger on the level of the nature of what this is subjected to?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The whole... this whole... this... all this presents is...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, where is that nature seen?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if what's in front of you... you can't see the danger, it's just fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, you can fabricate a danger, you can tell yourself,
[SPEAKER_02]: The future prospect will be in front of you...
[SPEAKER_01]: But then you're telling yourself it's dangerous, in order to try to... Get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: To try to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And basically that, you're trying to change it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, of course, of course.
[SPEAKER_02]: We can... we can address that later, but what I wanted to ask was...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you can't see the danger in what's... what's right in front of you... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: As in, the danger is not in the perception of it... No.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't see the danger, then, in the result of what's in front of you, because there's just going to be
[SPEAKER_01]: Where is that... where do you look for the danger?
[SPEAKER_01]: Peripherally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Peripherally in regard to what?
[SPEAKER_01]: In regard to what's present.
[SPEAKER_02]: What's present and enduring.
[SPEAKER_02]: What's present and enduring, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's why knowledge, peripheral, background, are all become basically synonymous almost.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's where understanding takes place.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can examine things through a perception all you want, but you don't understand what is subjected to.
[SPEAKER_02]: And what is subjected to is that which cannot be seen on the level of that thing, because it becomes the thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Something else is that subjected to.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't see, oh, this thing is subjected to change.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't see that in the perception of the thing, because it's already secondary to its nature.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just can't perceive it like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if you... all you do is perception, perception, focusing, focusing, sensation, sensations, nostrils, nostrils... No, that's why understanding feeling... that's why I was talking about understanding feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You understand feeling by having this, eh... And not just that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Seeing the... seeing the... this nature of change.
[SPEAKER_02]: Nature, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Peripherally, in regard to this... As we said, you can only see the nature of change once you stop interfering with the feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Stop trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's right, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Stop indulging it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, stop being unrestrained.
[SPEAKER_02]: And stop trying to deny it through, like, overzealous restraint.
[SPEAKER_02]: And hence, the middle way.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you recognize the nature of feeling is to endure, then you can recognize what that nature, or rather, you can then recognize what that endurance is also subjected to.
[SPEAKER_02]: But in order to, as I said, in order to recognize this is subject to such and such,
[SPEAKER_02]: Qualities.
[SPEAKER_02]: Characteristics.
[SPEAKER_02]: You need to allow it to be there first.
[SPEAKER_02]: Enduring.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not have a view that it's momentarily changing, arising, passing, arising, passing, arising, passing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Those are completely separate things.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's there, remaining the same, while it is subjected to change.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's how you get to understand and feel the threat of the change.
[SPEAKER_02]: Feel the dukkha of nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's... yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's seeing the danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Look, look, look.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's changing.
[SPEAKER_02]: That is dukkha, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why this has to be rooted in the danger right now of the feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not after, not as a management, not as an explanation.
[SPEAKER_02]: And as you said, even when people say, oh, this is impermanent.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or the other one, the favorite, this too shall pass.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's another way of trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, this... Why would you be telling... Why would you be telling to yourself that this too shall pass?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're basically trying to convince yourself that the current pain will go away, will change.
[SPEAKER_02]: And why... Because you want it to change.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why would you want current pain to go away?
[SPEAKER_02]: Means you don't want it to be there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Means you're craving against it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_02]: For many people, practicing the dhamma, then, becomes just another form of management, which is another form of denial.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's not that... Or coping mechanism.
[SPEAKER_02]: But in order to...
[SPEAKER_02]: The fact that you're coping means you have to be affected first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: If your practice is based on the level of coping, you cannot possibly uproot what's affecting you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not so much that dukkha is anicca,
[SPEAKER_01]: That my pain is impermanent and will go away, I hope, in the future.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's anicca is dukkha.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the other way around.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's anicca is dukkha.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why we never mess around with the order of things.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's always anicca, dukkha, the experience of anatta.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is feeling permanent or is it impermanent?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is what is impermanent pleasant or painful?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And again, why are impermanent things unpleasant?
[SPEAKER_02]: Why is that which is anicca, why is that which is subjected to change, why is it unpleasant?
[SPEAKER_02]: Why can it be pleasant?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you don't want it to change like it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, you might want to change.
[SPEAKER_02]: As we said, when you suffer, you actually want the unpleasant feeling to change.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why is change unpleasant?
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't matter if it's changed for better or for worse.
[SPEAKER_02]: Change in itself is dukkha.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you don't have your say in it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can tell yourself all you want, that you have a say, you're in control.
[SPEAKER_02]: The fact is, you are subjected to change, because things change on their own, on their own accord.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's completely inaccessible to you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yet, you latch on to it, when it feels like it suits you, it suits your needs.
[SPEAKER_02]: In a nutshell, the fundamental reason for any action, any kamma, good or bad, is latching on to change.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why, if you free yourself from that nature of being subjected to change, you free yourself from action.
[SPEAKER_02]: You free yourself from acting out of it, out of that ignorance, out of that contradiction.
[SPEAKER_02]: You free yourself from kamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because your actions... because any... yeah, your kind of intentions, let's say, are now no longer rooted in wanting change, wanting things to change.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if you say, oh, this too shall pass, what's going to happen then when it passes?
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, there's this... whatever, I'm worried about impermanence, but it will pass.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: I tell to myself to help myself cope with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's going to happen afterwards?
[SPEAKER_01]: When this passes... Something else will.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what's going to happen then?
[SPEAKER_01]: Something else or something else.
[SPEAKER_02]: Something else.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then you realize that, like, when people do use this coping mechanism, the management techniques, even on the pretext of dhamma practice, all you can affect is content of things that bother you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, this too shall pass.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that will pass.
[SPEAKER_02]: Something else will take its place, while the nature of being subjected to change remains unchanged.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you are fully under its thumb.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha talks a lot about turning away from libidity, turning away from feeling, I'd say.
[SPEAKER_01]: Dispassion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, turning away, fading away, becoming dispassionate, cessation, liberation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, turning away from feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, you turn away from feeling,
[SPEAKER_01]: By turning away from wanting change.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's what I was thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not so much... it's not so much... You can't directly choose to turn away.
[SPEAKER_01]: Turning away from feeling, because... yeah, well, because feeling's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether you like it or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: But... and turning away there, and that sounds like...
[SPEAKER_01]: Pushing it away, you know, like, kind of not wanting it to be there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sure, it can be taken... Like, same, when Buddha would say, oh, he doesn't tolerate.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: The, like, you know, the thought of, uh, lust or ill will.
[SPEAKER_02]: People take that to mean, oh, you must deny it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, you don't tolerate.
[SPEAKER_02]: It means, I don't tolerate this, which is there, enduring in front of me.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you try to deny it, as if, oh, this shouldn't be there, this shouldn't be there, you're overstepping.
[SPEAKER_02]: It means
[SPEAKER_02]: Setting up in conditions that will result in turning you away.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And those conditions are full understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Seeing this thing as danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: Full understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Seeing this thing as danger.
[SPEAKER_02]: Full understanding of the nature of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And how did the Buddha describe full understanding?
[SPEAKER_02]: By seeing the extent of gratification, by seeing the extent of danger, by seeing the extent of escape.
[SPEAKER_02]: And by the way, he didn't
[SPEAKER_02]: He used the same principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: I've seen... he talks about... he talks about seeing the gratification, danger and escape from the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Six domains.
[SPEAKER_01]: Consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: The world.
[SPEAKER_01]: The element of earth.
[SPEAKER_01]: The gratification of the world.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the extent of its gratification, as in the extent of its affirmation, either through acceptance or denial, you still affirm it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That which you accept or deny.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the extent of danger implicit in you doing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not so much turning away from feeling, as seeing that this is something I don't want.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't want it, yeah, not welcoming.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if I don't want this, if I don't want to sort of step into this, and want to engage with it, and want to change it...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's important to emphasize that it's not on the level of choice.
[SPEAKER_02]: It cannot be on the level of choice.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you don't have to choose to not want danger.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just need to start to learn how to see the danger.
[SPEAKER_02]: Danger automatically means no passion.
[SPEAKER_02]: No passion automatically means no desire.
[SPEAKER_02]: If there is no desire, there is no wanting.
[SPEAKER_02]: If there is no basis of wanting, there is no basis for craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: If there is no craving in regard to feeling, there is no ownership of feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, that's complete dispassion, removal of any fire burning in regard to feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: Done.
[SPEAKER_02]: Understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: Understanding the danger on the right level in regard to right things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not secondarily, not as a level of management, not as an afterthought, not as a linear explanation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Everything fits beautifully, same as the modern science has proven.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Understanding why am I subjected to this danger, needs to be personal.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, whether it's the feeling you're contemplating, whether it's perception, whether it's the moods, whether it's sensual cravings, whether it's your will, for that matter, whether it's anything, understand the extent of gratification, the extent of danger will become apparent, the escape will be realized.
[SPEAKER_02]: The escape means removal of passion and delight in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, not delighting in feeling, for example, is the same thing as not, like, wanting it to change.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you know that whole
[SPEAKER_02]: It depends.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you say, like, oh, you don't want it to change, that can also mean, like, you're interfering with it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I want this to be more of what it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: I want this to remain the same as it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: As in, I want it to...
[SPEAKER_02]: But again, you're implying another layer of that feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, although you think you're not wanting change, you're still acting out of change.
[SPEAKER_02]: Change that you don't want.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, whether you affirm, whether you deny change, you accept it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's revolving around it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're revolving around it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you want to see the danger in the change.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't matter whether it changes, how quickly, when, for better or for worse, or changes just to remain the same a bit more.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: What matters is seeing the danger in that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not in the content, not in the result, but in the nature of being subject to change.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's like Sotāpanna's insight.
[SPEAKER_02]: Basically, the insight that qualifies you, that makes you Sotāpanna is,
[SPEAKER_02]: Whatever, whatever has a nature to manifest, as in to change on its own, to appear on its own, that's why it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because of that nature, not because of the content, because I analyzed its atomic structure and proven that it will disintegrate.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because the experience of disintegration has manifested for you.
[SPEAKER_02]: The experience of destruction has manifested for you.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's not anicca.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because the experience of destruction, I'm destroying these things, is of a nature to change.
[SPEAKER_02]: The experience of construction is of a nature to change.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's just basically seeing the pain of impermanence.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: If impermanence is seen correctly, it is felt unpleasantly.
[SPEAKER_02]: If that which is seen correctly felt unpleasantly, that experience cannot be taken as mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, there is no room for after.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's funny, isn't it, how many people
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, I remember, you know, years and years ago, when I started meditating, and it was like, anicca was like, everything's changing, and it all just, like, feels really pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a denial of reality, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, now, there's no mother, there's no father.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why I meditate to have this pleasant feeling of everything's just changing.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is no pain, because everything is constantly changing.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's exactly, it falls into those
[SPEAKER_02]: Some have understood the wrong views that they would have described.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nobody dies, nobody lives, everything is constantly changing, constant, constant state of flux.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing matters.
[SPEAKER_02]: How can you even utter a sentence?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: If everything is constantly changing, your sentence will be meaningless by the time it reaches its end.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it isn't.
[SPEAKER_02]: You get the meaning, which is clearly not changing for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yet, you go around saying everything is changing.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's the view that doesn't change for you.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, that's the view that endures.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you enable yourself to deny it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything except for this view.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: You enable yourself to deny it by focusing on the content of things, making a meditation about the content, your mindfulness about staring at the content, so you don't have to look at nature and basically become aware of your responsibility for choosing to hold that view.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like that man who came to the Buddha and said... the Buddha asked him, what view do you have?
[SPEAKER_02]: He said, well, my view is that nothing pleases me.
[SPEAKER_02]: My view is that everything changes, constantly, every second of the time.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then we can easily say, well, that really doesn't change for you.
[SPEAKER_02]: In the same sense, he said, oh, well, that view pleases you then, that nothing pleases me.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can even conceive anything then.
[SPEAKER_02]: They will not be subjected to the danger of change.
[SPEAKER_02]: They will not
[SPEAKER_02]: I take in the nature of danger of change.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, no, because anything I conceive now is contained within this situation that we're seeing here.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, see, anything you conceive, say, anything, any thought that pops up in your head.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: There you go.
[SPEAKER_02]: Popping up.
[SPEAKER_02]: You cannot create it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: It appears for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Can you conceive anything that it's of a nature to appear?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: To not shape the nature of abrupt change.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because appearance is already a form of abrupt change.
[SPEAKER_01]: Actually, manifesting means... That's what it means.
[SPEAKER_01]: ...change.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you realize there's absolutely nothing conceivable that you can regard as not subject to change.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, you can't conceive anything as permanent, as the people would translate.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or as not dangerous.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's all implicit.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you say that the change you want, it's always like the forefront.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want things in the forefront to change.
[SPEAKER_00]: But change actually happens where you can't... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what I mean when I say you can only deal, aim at the content.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I want the change because you projected desire onto the content of what you want to change.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why sensuality kind of gets you locked on sense objects, and it's completely not in them.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's in your dependence on that delight in change.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yet, you think it's in the things you can touch, see, taste, and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it isn't.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not the slightest.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not even a grain of it can spill into the material.
[SPEAKER_02]: Inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: In any case, the change you're subject to, you try to conceive that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, you're not trying to conceive it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're conceiving it basically by overlooking it.
[SPEAKER_02]: By putting it in the content, you have misconceived it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Any form of misconceiving is conceiving is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you misconceive it to be there.
[SPEAKER_02]: You misconceive pleasure to be contained in things, in response to this unpleasant desire.
[SPEAKER_02]: You misconceive, misconceive.
[SPEAKER_02]: Misconceiving means contradiction.
[SPEAKER_02]: Any misconceiving means conceiving is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why... or you could say, conceiving means misconceiving.
[SPEAKER_02]: And saṃsarāhānta is free from conceivings, free from contradictions, on that existential level.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, like, again, it's not like you have to figure out and sort of, you know, cast a net that's gonna scoop all the conceivings out.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just need to stop entertaining passion through your ignorant acts, for which you're responsible.
[SPEAKER_02]: There always... You can't do... You can't engage with lust, aversion, delusion, accidentally.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's always on the basis of your choice.
[SPEAKER_02]: Always.
[SPEAKER_02]: You stop feeding those states of mind through your choice, and you will do so if you find a good reason to not do it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You are then removing the basis for maintenance of those misconceptions.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why sīla has to come first.
[SPEAKER_02]: Absolutely not negotiable in any shape or form.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why practice never leaves that container of sīla.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not like, oh, I've developed sīla, now I'll go and figure this out.
[SPEAKER_02]: Develop sīla, understand it, that's it, that's what it means, figuring it out.
[SPEAKER_02]: Once you understood the basis of non-lust, non-aversion, non-delusion, it's irreversible.
[SPEAKER_02]: You cannot engage with lust, aversion and delusion anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because to do that is always to basically want things to change.
[SPEAKER_01]: Always.
[SPEAKER_02]: Always.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why both, like, uh, meritorious and demeritorious actions partake within kamma, partake within this principle of being subjected to change in ownership and you craving for it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, there's a good action, there's a bad action.
[SPEAKER_02]: Either way, action is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Acting for change is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Can you act out of wanting this to change?
[SPEAKER_02]: If you have no desire, no conceivable desire for this, I could change it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why it also ties in with the wrong view that you are the master controller.
[SPEAKER_02]: See, you're subjected to change because of which you want change, because of which you act, and then change happens abruptly to you, but it's... you start regarding it because you acted.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why it happens to you.
[SPEAKER_02]: But why did you act in the first place?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you were subjected to things you couldn't prevent.
[SPEAKER_02]: So then, your action is secondary.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your ownership is secondary to that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, basically, your ownership is fully within the container that you cannot conceive outside of, let alone own.
[SPEAKER_02]: And control it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you forget that, and all you start seeing is me acting and things changing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, I am here.
[SPEAKER_02]: I am mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: These things are... do belong to me.
[SPEAKER_02]: I am the master.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, look, I can break this.
[SPEAKER_02]: I can create this.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I might not be able to change that or this, but I can change this.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Some things I can change.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, therefore, I'm still in control here.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's more than enough.
[SPEAKER_02]: Again, but if you were to ask yourself honestly, so which is more then?
[SPEAKER_02]: Things you can't change or things you can change?
[SPEAKER_01]: I was like, oh, crap.
[SPEAKER_02]: Things I
[SPEAKER_02]: Ability to change is fully enclosed within the vast sea of things that you cannot even conceive how to change.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's secondary.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if ownership is... if mastery is secondary, it's not mastery, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, I'm enslaved by this, but I tell myself I'm a master of this.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm in this prison cell, but I'm free to walk up there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can lay, I can stand, I can sit.
[SPEAKER_02]: I am my own man.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm free.
[SPEAKER_00]: In that door, like, you're only subject to that when you think you have a say in what you've been subjected to, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that has to be implicit.
[SPEAKER_02]: It has to be implicit.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why you maintain these kind of implicit views through your careless action.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you have to stop maintaining, stop providing basis for those views through your, again, volitional choice of lust, aversion and distraction.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you stop maintaining it, then, yeah, you won't be able to feed these implicit beliefs.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, yeah, if you are not already implying that you can master, that you can take possession of change, you wouldn't have any desire and lust towards wanting things to change.
[SPEAKER_02]: It would be inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why freedom from desire and lust is freedom from ownership, freedom from the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: That you are always trying to change something.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Can't possibly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's... that's actually... there's always the reason for the suffering, for the pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's absolutely nothing... nothing else.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: Freedom from it is pretty much a universal goal.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even for people who...
[SPEAKER_02]: choose to go about it by proliferating their suffering, and lust, and aversion, and distraction, and chasing sensuality.
[SPEAKER_02]: They still do it for the reason because they want to be free from the pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: Pain of not having enough of what you want.
[SPEAKER_02]: Pain of having more than enough of what you don't want.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or as the Buddha said, pain of being...
[SPEAKER_02]: Separated from the things that are desirable, likable, and pain of being united with things that are unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: Anything's perception, not just this thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's on the level of the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so we... the Buddha also talks about seeing the danger of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a different way of talking about the same principle.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Gratification, danger, escape from the eyes, sights, and everything dependent on that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whichever aspect, particular aspect of it you might take, the nature is the same.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's what you're supposed to discern.
[SPEAKER_02]: Stay focusing on a particular aspect that will somehow reveal you the truth, magically.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the contemplation of death, quite, quite...
[SPEAKER_00]: Straightforwardly undermines that, doesn't it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah, sharply.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, it will be hard to... if you do the contemplation of that correctly, it will be very hard to then maintain all these misconceptions we're talking about.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then, yeah, it might be a bit too much too soon for some people, if they haven't developed virtue beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Isn't it this sort of... it's the same principle, really, talking about death is just that kind of abrupt change?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, just different way of arriving at the... at the discernment of the same principle.
[SPEAKER_02]: Basically, death is that fundamental... doesn't matter how much I control, I can...
[SPEAKER_02]: I can exercise, I can apply.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's all within a very, very perilous space that is subjected to ultimate non-control.
[SPEAKER_02]: Death.
[SPEAKER_02]: Anicca.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if something is fundamentally, cannot escape, subject of abrupt change, whichever way, is that something you can regard as, oh, this is mine, dear to me, personal, intimate?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: All those attitudes require a degree of
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, conceived permanence, conceived ownership, conceived control, conceived possession.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only reason why you can do that is because you're not seeing what it's all underlined by.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you're not seeing what it's all underlined by because you're actively choosing to ignore it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's avijjā.
[SPEAKER_02]: Another metaphysical maya, veil of illusion.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a choice to distract yourself from the unpleasant truth.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, exactly, because it's more pleasant to avoid that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And focus on the minor, you know, illusion of control, where I can get a bit of pleasure out of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like the leper, the... Getting the satisfaction, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And investing his whole life in building elaborate fire pits where he can burn his skin and find enjoyment.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's usually, basically, building a home and life based on sensuality, which is pretty much everyone's life.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: While in reality, all of it is done because of pain and fear.
[SPEAKER_02]: And in itself remains painful and fearful.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you choose to kind of... people choose to
[SPEAKER_01]: To not look at that danger, that fear.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereas, actually, that is what they need to look at in order to free themselves from it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: They choose to not look at it because that's the only way of freedom from it that they know.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's not freedom, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's making... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's making it worse.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's making it... next time, making it even harder to look away from it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then, you have to double down.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whether it's a bhutujana or an arahant, as the Buddha said in that sutta, Majjhima 13, I think, everyone wants to be free from affliction.
[SPEAKER_01]: How does he say that?
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: But only when you reach, like, the level of samādhi and sensuality, developing the proper understanding of
[SPEAKER_02]: Then you realize, ah, this is truly the beginning of freedom from affliction.
[SPEAKER_02]: Nothing less than this.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then they realize, yeah, I always wanted to be free from affliction.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why I was engaging with sensuality.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it was afflicting me.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's just that.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only way I knew was to go down towards it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like keep... keeping alive.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, we don't want that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Delete that bit.
[SPEAKER_02]: Delete.
[SPEAKER_02]: Backspace, backspace.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, even if somebody is overwhelmed, doesn't know how to practice, where to practice, what to do, it's just too much, all these aggregates, nāmarūpas and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_02]: One thing you can know for sure is, if I
[SPEAKER_02]: Willingly, mindfully, carefully, choose to not engage with things that are rooted in motivation based on greed, motivation based on aversion, motivation based on careless distraction.
[SPEAKER_02]: I am actually practicing the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if I just go around mechanically and hoping for results to happen to me, and certainly ignoring my responsibility for my own choices, including choice of sīla, choice of practice, choice of restraint, well, then I'm not practicing the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if I actually wear robes and do everything by the book.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm not doing it in the right order, not doing it on the right level.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can spend the whole day.
[SPEAKER_02]: Again, as a layperson, who doesn't necessarily has any, like, you know, more detailed understanding of the suttas and what to do, well, you can spend the whole day being mindful of motivation behind your actions.
[SPEAKER_02]: And before you're about to do something, you, like, investigate, ask yourself, why are you doing?
[SPEAKER_02]: What is the purpose of this?
[SPEAKER_02]: Every little thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: You wanna go out for a walk.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't matter I shouldn't or I should.
[SPEAKER_02]: What matters is to know why.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, well, because, you know, the doctor told me I need to exercise.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is that a valid enough reason?
[SPEAKER_02]: Maybe.
[SPEAKER_02]: How do you determine it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, is it rooted in wholesome or unwholesome?
[SPEAKER_02]: Is it rooted in lust, aversion or distraction?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or is it rooted in necessity?
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Why do you need to be alive?
[SPEAKER_02]: Why do you need to maintain your health?
[SPEAKER_02]: Is that a goal in itself, maybe?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or is it because you have a greater purpose that health is required as a basis to perform that purpose?
[SPEAKER_02]: To make you feel responsible for whatever you do.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then you might choose not to go for a walk, or you might choose to go for a walk.
[SPEAKER_02]: But either way, you won't be ignorant in regard to your choices.
[SPEAKER_02]: You won't be ignorant in regard to your action by body, speech or mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's practice of dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whether you know it or not, whether you call it like that or not, that is practice of dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the thing, like, whenever you have an answer, if you know that... Then you question it further.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's the thing, like, if you... if you're going on explaining it further and further, you know you're already... That starts... Oh, hold on!
[SPEAKER_02]: Why am I, like, so keen on explaining this?
[SPEAKER_02]: Why am I... why was I triggered by this question?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because I want to cover things up for me.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why are you covering up always?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's your responsibility.
[SPEAKER_02]: Always.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because the responsibility is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why Buddha said ignorance will accumulate the burden, the burden of responsibility.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the weight.
[SPEAKER_02]: The more you ignore it, the heavier it gets.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it seems sharper, more painful once you stop ignoring it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But actually, you start de-accumulating it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's how you truly de-accumulate your karma, by accepting responsibility for it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't de-accumulate your karma by, you know, making random offerings and cancelling the negative balance of your bank account.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're making good karma, but bad karma cannot be undone simply by performing good karma.
[SPEAKER_02]: The only way to undo the bad karma is to fully accept responsibility for it and then free yourself through understanding of it, whereby it doesn't apply to you.
[SPEAKER_02]: And there is no amount of action you can do to compensate for that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Only freedom from action can free you from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: A good kamma can be less pressing, but still pressing.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why it's a good kamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's still a kamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's still a burden.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it won't last forever.
[SPEAKER_02]: The result of the good burden.
[SPEAKER_02]: Pleasant burden.
[SPEAKER_02]: Light burden.
[SPEAKER_02]: Agreeable burden.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, Ken, it's about seeing the danger in kamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Seeing the danger in ignoring things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Seeing the daydream turning away from clarity of your motivation, turning away from the clarity of things that are felt unpleasantly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that's why you would turn away from clarity.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not because of some universe, like, mistake of the universe.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it's unpleasant to admit it first.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And just because of that tiny little, deep attitude, whole mass of suffering,
[SPEAKER_02]: For eons and eons and eons and eons to come for many people.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just because of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, it's a bit complicated.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the avijjā, you know, the avijjā, the avijjā, is always in the present moment, literally.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not past avijjā, in the sense that you are not maintaining through the present avijjā.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Present ignoring is where your responsibility is.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why you can free yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: If your vijjā were truly past ignorings of things, that's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's solidified in the past.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't uproot that.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it isn't.
[SPEAKER_02]: The only reason that past ignorings still have the weight of ignorings is because you are now still partaking in the same nature of ignoring.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, once you're free... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Same with sensuality, when...
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't know, maybe a different sutra.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think it was the Leper Sutra.
[SPEAKER_02]: And all the sensuality that he remembers from before that provided him great joy, was actually pain.
[SPEAKER_02]: He sees the past sensuality as painful.
[SPEAKER_02]: All the future sensuality that would have been, would have been painful.
[SPEAKER_02]: Cannot step outside of that domain.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's fully enclosed within the painful domain.
[SPEAKER_02]: And now that became apparent.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it doesn't mean like before I had the pure sensuality when I was engaging in it.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, past is seen against the backdrop of the present understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: Future is seen against the backdrop of the present understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: Present is seen against the backdrop of the present understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.